Guide to the Vladimir Ussachevsky papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Vladimir Ussachevsky Papers,
1932-1969
Ussachevsky, Vladimir, 1911-1990.
8.25 linear ft. ( 14 document boxes and 1 flat box ).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1492
7583223
The Vladimir Ussachevsky Papers document the academic and professional career of pioneering electronic-music composer Vladimir Ussachevsky. This collection contains teaching and administrative materials, correspondence with other composers, writings and compositions by Ussachevsky and others, and programs, publicity materials, and personal documents.
Biographical Note
Vladimir Ussachevsky was born in 1911 in the Russian province of Outer Manchuria, where his father was serving as a career officer in the Russian Army. Ussachevsky's mother performed and gave lessons on the piano, and she became her son's first teacher, initiating his musical education in piano and Russian Orthodox choral music. After playing in restaurants and vaudeville theaters as a teenager in Manchuria, Vladimir emigrated to California with his mother and siblings in 1930. Although he had intended to study electrical engineering, he became fascinated with composition while at Pomona College, where he received his B.A. in 1935. Ussachevsky then pursued graduate studies at the Eastman School of Music in Rochester, New York, studying with Howard Hanson among others. Ussachevsky returned briefly to California in the early 1940s after receiving his Ph.D. to care for his ailing mother. He taught high-school and junior-college music classes there before enlisting in the United States Army in September 1942 for the duration World War II.
After the war Ussachevsky began his long association with Columbia University, coming to New York in the fall of 1947 as an instructor and post-doctoral student under Otto Luening. At first, he taught introductory courses and continued to compose chamber, piano, and choral works in what he later called a "pseudo-Romantic Russian style." Ussachevsky's longstanding interest in electrical engineering, however, led him to pursue a radical new direction in composition. As his student Robert Moog recalled, "The department had acquired its first tape recorder, an Ampex 400, and Vladimir was assigned to care for it. After using it extensively to record live performances, he began looking for new ways to use the tape machine. He created new musical sounds by speed changing, playing segments of tape backwards, splicing, looping, and electronic processing, and then assembled the sounds into experimental compositions." His tape compositions, many of them collaborations with Luening, were first performed in 1952, garnering Ussachevsky acclaim among both the New York musical community and the emerging transnational network of electronic music composers.
Inspired by his contacts with Pierre Schaefer, the creator of musique concrete, and electronic music composers in Russia, Ussachevsky along with fellow composers Luening, Milton Babbitt, and Roger Sessions founded in 1959 the Columbia-Princeton Electronic Music Center (CPEMC), which was modeled on Schaefer's Centre d'Etudes Radiophoniques in Paris. According to Moog, himself a major innovator in the field, Ussachevsky and engineer Peter Mauzey built equipment and developed technical practices of the highest possible quality, assisted by the funding of the Rockefeller Foundation and technical support from Bell Laboratories. Until his retirement from Columbia in 1980, Ussachevsky directed the CPEMC and mentored hundreds of students in theory and composition, most notably Moog and the composer Wendy Carlos. Ussachevsky also became a tireless crusader in the promotion of electronic music, presenting lecture-demonstrations at colleges and universities across the United States and Canada.
Outside of Columbia, Ussachevsky continued actively to pursue a composing career, writing scores of works for orchestras and choral groups, almost all of them incorporating the tape medium. Ussachevsky contributed musical settings for film, television, theater and poetry, collaborating with Clifton Fadiman, John Houseman, Stan Brakhage, Louis Zukofsky, Orson Welles, Alfred Hitchcock, and Burgess Meredith among others. He also played an active role in several artist organizations, principally the American Composers' Alliance and the MacDowell Colony, and served as editor for the journal New Music Edition.
After retiring from Columbia in 1980, he remained as a tenured professor at the University of Utah, where he had been Composer-in-Residence since 1970. He was married to the poet Elizabeth ("Betty") Kray from 1947 until her death in 1987. The couple had no children. Ussachevsky died on January 4, 1990 in New York City, remembered as a seminal figure in the development of electronic music in the United States.
Scope and Content
This collection consists primarily of teaching and administrative materials from Ussachevsky's tenure as a professor at Columbia, including materials related to the Columbia-Princeton Electronic Music Center: equipment catalogs, memos, correspondence, schematics, intellectual content, and grant requests. There are also documents of Ussachevsky's professional activities outside of Columbia including: correspondence, board minutes, and newsletters from composer organizations; and programs, press releases, and news clippings that document performances of his works as well as concerts he attended, especially among the post-war American avant-garde. A sub-series of Ussachevsky's writings contains his published articles and notes for articles on musicology and tape music, and notebooks from his graduate studies.
The collection also includes several draft scores in manuscript of Ussachevsky's compositions, supplemented with sketches, notebooks, and textual sources that informed his works. There is also an extensive selection of music journals collected by Ussachevsky during the 1950s and 1960s, including rare foreign-language items that he acquired in his European travels. A series dedicated to personal files contains a cross-section of personal and professional correspondence that depicts the networks of composers, writers, artists, and technicians that made up Ussachevsky's milieu. There are a few folders of personal items, mostly related to the finances of him and his wife.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in five series.
Series I. Academic Activities, 1937-1969
Subseries I.1. Academic Career, 1937-1969
Subseries I.2. Columbia-Princeton Electronic Music Center, 1949-1968
Series II. Professional Activities, 1932-1969
Subseries II.1. Associations, 1938-1969
Subseries II.2. Publicity and Performances, 1949-1969
Subseries II.3. Writings, 1932-1964
Series III. Compositions, 1937-1960s
Subseries III.1. Compositions, 1937-1960s
Subseries III.2. Compositions by Others, 1950s
Series IV. Personal Files, 1934-1968
Series V. Printed Material, 1936-1969 [Bulk Dates: 1949-1969]
Related Material--Other Institutions
Vladimir Ussachevsky Collection, Music Division, Library of Congress [unprocessed].
Subjects
Columbia University; Eastman School of Music; MacDowell Colony (Petersborough, N.H.)--History; Rockefeller Foundation; Babbitt, Milton, 1916-; Bartok, Bela, 1881-1945--Criticism and interpretation--Congresses; Berio, Luciano, 1925-2003; Brakhage, Stan--Friends and associates; Luening, Otto, 1900-1996; Schaeffer, Pierre, 1910-1995; Seeger, Charles, 1886-1979; Ussachevsky, Vladimir, 1911-1990; Zukofsky, Louis, 1904-1978--Musical Settings; Audio amplifiers; Composers--France; Composers--United States--Biography; Composers--United States--Societies, etc.; Composition (Music)--20th century; Electronic Music; Music--20th century--History and criticism; Music--Acoustics and physics--Congresses; Music--Instruction and study--United States--History; Musicology--United States--History--20th century; Musique Concrète--History and criticism
Access Restrictions
Box 3, Folder 4 is restricted until 2040, otherwise, the collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
Antonia Bryson Gift 2000 February 1999-2000-32
- Series I: Academic Activities, 1937-1969
  - Subseries I.1: Academic Career, 1937-1969
    - Student Papers
      - Essays, 1937-1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - General, 1937-1955, (3 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 2 to 4)
      - Barnard Counterpoint, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - GS Music 37, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - General, 1952-1960, (3 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 7 to 9)
      - General, 1955, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 10 to 11)
      - Music 37, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - GS Music 38, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Blue Books, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Musicianship, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Regina Weiss, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - General, 1956, (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 4 to 5)
      - General, 1956-1959 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Counterpoint 210, 1956-1961 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - General, 1956-1963, (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 8 to 9)
      - 20th-Century Music, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - GS Music 38, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Humanities, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Music 35-36, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Grade Sheets, circa 1950s (Box 3, Folder 4)
        [Restricted until 2040]
    - Teaching Materials
      - Eastman School of Music, 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Pasadena Junior College and Roosevelt High, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Theory Seminar, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Seminar, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Music 23, Music History, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Humanities MB1, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Assignments in Modern Music, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Music 38, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Humanities RMB1, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Music 1, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - GS Music 17, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - General, circa 1950s (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Mimeograph Exercises, circa 1950s (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Columbia University--Administration Materials, 1949-1968, (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Columbia Department of Music
      - General, 1952-1967, (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 3 to 4)
      - Bartok Forum, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Mozart Festival, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Sang Prize Submissions, 1969, (4 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 7 to 10)
      - Catalogs of Textbooks and Scores, 1950s-1960s, (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 1 to 2)
  - Subseries I.2: Columbia-Princeton Electronic Music Center, 1949-1968
    - Administrative Files--General, 1949-1969, (6 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 3 to 8)
    - Printed Materials, 1955-1968 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Centre d’Etudes Radiophoniques, 1953-1957 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Second International Commission on Acoustics Congress, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Preliminary Report to the Rockefeller Foundation, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Intellectual Content, 1950s-1960s (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Equipment Catalogs--Audio Fair Materials, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Equipment Catalogs--General, 1955-1969 (2 of 4 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 7 to 8)
    - Equipment Catalogs--General, 1955-1969 (2 of 4 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 1 to 2)
- Series II: Professional Activities, 1932-1969
  - Subseries II.1: Associations, 1938-1969
    - Composer Organizations
      - American Composers Alliance, 1955-1968 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - MacDowell Colony, 1949-1969 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - New Music Edition, 1948-1961 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - General, 1949-1968 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Trip to Russia, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Programs of Others, 1938-1969 (1 of 3 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Programs of Others, 1938-1969 (2 of 3 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Programs--Conferences and Lectures, 1953-1966, (2 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 3 to 4)
    - Press Releases of Others, 1960s (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Associations--General, 1951-1968 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Subseries II.2: Publicity and Performances, 1949-1969
    - Biographical Information, 1950s-1960s (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Press Releases and Articles, 1952-1967 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - "Back to Methuselah"--Correspondence and Publicity, 1957-1958 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Programs, 1949-1969, Undated (1 of 5 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Programs, 1949-1969, Undated (4 of 5 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 1 to 4)
    - News Clippings, 1952-1967, (2 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 5 to 6)
  - Subseries II.3: Writings, 1932-1964
    - Articles--Published, 1958-1960 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Articles and Lectures--Drafts, 1950s-1960s (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - "Tape Music"--Notes and Drafts, 1950s (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Writings by Others
      - "Des Machines a créer de la Musique," by M.A. Moles, 1958 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - "Systematic Musicology," by Charles Seeger, 1951 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - "Preface to a Description of a Music," by Charles Seeger, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - "Die informationtheoretisch," by VonFritz Winckel, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Conservatory Materials
      - Piano Lessons, 1932 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - General, 1932 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - Sibelius Symphonies, 1936-1937 (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - General, 1938-1939, (2 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 8 to 9)
      - Nef’s Outline, 1930s (Box 10, Folder 10)
      - General, 1930s (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Notes from Paul Henry Lang Course, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Series III: Compositions, 1937-1960s
  - Subseries III.1: Compositions, 1937-1960s
    - "Jubilee Cantata," printed score, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - "Piano Concerto," draft score, [1950s] (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Notes and Schematics for New York Philharmonic Concert, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Notes for Compositions--General, 1950s and 1960s (2 of 3 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 16 to 17)
    - Notes for Compositions--General, 1950s and 1960s (1 of 3 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Notebooks, 1950s and 1960s (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Score Notebooks, 1950s and 1960s, (2 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 3 to 4)
    - Textual Sources
      - "Mexican Christmas," 1941 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - "The Creation," 1960s (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - "Finian’s Rainbow," 1960s (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - "Material for Cantata," 1960 (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - "Mongolian Prince," undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - General, circa 1960s (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Untitled Draft Scores, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Subseries III.2: Compositions by Others, 1950s
    - En Blanc et Noir by Claude Debussy, printed score (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Twelve Pieces for Piano by Keith Robinson, manuscript score, 1950s (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Holidays Symphony by Charles Ives, parts (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Students, circa 1950s (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Printed Scores by Others, 1950s (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Series IV: Personal Files, 1934-1968
  - Correspondence
    - Special Correspondence, 1942-1964 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - 1936-1954 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - College Lecture Tour, 1954-55 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - 1955-1957, (2 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 15 to 17)
    - 1958-1968, (4 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 1 to 4)
    - Undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Family, 1955-1965 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - By Others, 1942-1964 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Financial Documents, 1934-1967 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Personal Files--General, 1950s (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Holiday Cards, 1950s (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, 1950s-1960s (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Travel Memorabilia, 1949-1968 (Box 12, Folder 12)
- Series V: Printed Materials, 1936-1969 (Bulk 1949-1969)
  - Journals
    - American Composer Alliance Bulletin, 1955-1958 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - A-D, 1958-1967 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - D-I, 1956-1969 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Journal of the Acoustical Society of America, 1957-1962, (3 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 3 to 5)
    - Journal of the Acoustical Society of America, 1962-1963 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - J, 1954-1966 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - J, 1955-1966 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - J-M, 1936-1960 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - M, 1951-1960 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Origin, 1961 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - R, 1949-1967 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - S-T, 1956-1967 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Foreign Language Journals
    - Cybernetics and Music-Musik Revy, 1951-1963 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Technica, 1956 (Box 14, Folder 10)